[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the Middle Length Discourse, number 40.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Shorter Discourse at Asapuddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha goes on saying, recluses, recluses, because that is how people perceive you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you are asked, what are you?
[SPEAKER_00]: You claim that you are recluses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Since that is what you are designated and what you claim to be, you should train thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: We will practice the way proper to the recluse, so that our designations may be true and our claims genuine, and so that the services of those whose robes, alms food, resting place and medicines we use, shall bring them great fruit and benefit, and so that our going forth shall not be vain, but fruitful and fertile.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how does a bhikkhu not practice the way proper to the rec... to the recluse?
[SPEAKER_00]: For so long as a bhikkhu who is covetous, has not abandoned covetousness, who has a mind of ill will... ill will, and has not abandoned ill will, who has a mind of full with defilements, and has not abandoned defilements,
[SPEAKER_00]: I say because of his failure to abandon these stains for the recluse, these faults for the recluse, which are grounds for rebirth in a state of deprivation and whose results are to be experienced in an unhappy destination.
[SPEAKER_00]: I do not say that the recluse's status comes about in a rag-robe wearer, through the mere wearing of rag-robes, nor in, well, basically any ascetic practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't become an ascetic through... You don't become a recluse through asceticism.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through asceticism, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: By standing on one leg.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it is, if through the mere wearing of rag robes, one who is a rag robe wearer, who was covetousness, covetous, abandoned covetousness, then his friends and companions and kinsmen and relatives would make him a rag robe as soon as he was born and have him undertake the rag robe wearing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus,
[SPEAKER_00]: Come, my dear, be a rag-robe wearer, so that by mere wearing of a rag-robe, when you are defiled, you will abandon defilement.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you have wrong view, you abandon wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be that easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The work would be done for you, through wearing the... just wearing the rag-robes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so going...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and how does a bhikkhu practice the way proper to a recluse?
[SPEAKER_00]: When a bhikkhu who has a defilement, abandons the defilement, he has wrong view and he abandons wrong view, then he practices the way proper to the recluse.
[SPEAKER_00]: He sees himself purified of all these evil, unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: He sees himself liberated from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he sees this, gladness is born in him.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he's glad, rapture is born in him.
[SPEAKER_00]: In one who is rapturous, enjoys, the body becomes tranquil.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, that very thing you just read, kind of, on one hand, it sounds obvious, self-explanatory,
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, on the other hand, nobody seems to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, like, even people who are committed to the practice, they don't see, directly, that these states are abandoned, and then their gladness results.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all based on some sort of faith, approximation of, I'll do this, then this will happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll practice this, then I might have experience of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But a direct knowledge, recognition of this is wholesome, this is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unwholesome is abandoned, because of that I'm glad, and raptured, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's completely absent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although, it's an obvious passage, like you can read it, as you just did, and okay, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not many people would recognize that's all to it, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all the work that needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within that line you just read.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not elsewhere, not before or after, or in some different moods.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding unwholesome, and then abandoning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then knowing there are no unwholesome states present, and that gives rise automatically to gladness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you feel like you've done the work, the right work.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the only reason, natural conclusion is, the only reason why people wouldn't be seeing that and would be doing all sorts of other practices and methods and techniques and faiths and traditions and whatnot, is because they don't understand what wholesome is, nor unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: First thing, if you ask someone, do you know what ill-will is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes or no?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the whole point, is...
[SPEAKER_01]: But putujana needs to recognize putujana, which means his
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowledge of ill-will is not the right knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: His knowledge of non-ill-will is not the right knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: His knowledge of sensuality, of non-sensuality, his knowledge of right view and wrong view, are not the right knowledges.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, nobody denies that somebody who started a practice, or been practicing for a long time, but still a bhutujjana, doesn't know anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if they're still not sotāpanna,
[SPEAKER_01]: They themselves should not regard their knowledge as valid.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, they will keep making effort further, until they verify it with their own, like, basic understanding of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what every person should be questioning themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm reading all these suttas about ill-will, and here I am talking, like, I should do this, I should do that, but do we even know what a phenomenon of ill-will is?
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I designating when I say ill will?
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I referring to?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it a state of mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just don't look for information to stand for the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just ask yourself, what is it in your very experience at the same time that you are pointing at when you say this ill will?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it a pressure in your chest?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it a redness in your face?
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you look closely, you realize, well, it can't be that, because those are the results of the ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's... like... people think that putujana can become sotāpanna through, kind of, upgrading their understanding, you know, getting the... the more accurate truth based on what you... what you, kind of, know about the life, getting... getting greater insights into higher...
[SPEAKER_00]: Universal nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's completely the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pūtujana can become Sotāpanna when he completely undoes everything that makes him Pūtujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not when he builds on top of it the new ideas and new views and new experiences, but when he really undoes all of it that he is.
[SPEAKER_01]: With instruction from the suttas, that state, then, is where the right view can take place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for example, if someone says, is my mind filled with ill-will?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order... exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cannot... am I... am I... am I engaging in ill-will now?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say yes or no, but then you go further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, but... you'll understand what ill-will is.
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I asking myself here?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a lack of that kind of right reflection on the basic nature of designation and terms that you already use, that a bhaktuṣa already uses.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why he keeps maintaining his wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because he hasn't make... made enough effort invested in some technique or... or practice of restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: He probably made too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that can make any fundamental difference, because he hasn't uprooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just took aspects of those views for granted and then started his practice as building further on top of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, no matter how many stories you built, you built it on completely improper foundations.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't go as sufficiently high, because foundations can't support it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of trying to find out the answers, you really need to understand what do you... what are you even asking?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you referring to when you ask these questions?
[SPEAKER_01]: And ill-will was just one example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just take any of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ask yourself about your own feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you say, oh, I'm feeling like this today.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, don't worry about the content of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just think about the designation of word, feeling, that you used.
[SPEAKER_01]: In whatever language you would have used it, and ask yourself, okay, but what am I... what am I referring to?
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I pointing at?
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I designating with this designation of my language in this experience?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is that feeling that I just said, it's such and such?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I describe it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I understand it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I see its nature?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, no, the feeling is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's all great.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all what you heard.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all your information, your third-person view, your theory.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is necessary to have, but if you stay on the level of it, it can never really result in an insight that matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to see, for you, at the time of saying, my feeling is such and such, what do you refer to when you say that feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How far you can designate it, how far you can discern it, without... then everything else you think about a feeling is put it aside,
[SPEAKER_01]: First, start seeing what is being experienced as a feeling, when you say feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when the suttas, when sometimes, when the monks would try to understand something, they would say it out loud, like, like, oh, feeling, feeling, what is feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or first jhāna, first jhāna, what is first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Say it out loud.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you bring it to your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once, twice, three times.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, okay, so now, this enduring experience of having just said this out loud, within this enduring experience, I can
[SPEAKER_01]: Hopefully, start discerning the direction where that feeling actually is.
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I referring to?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize that any of the five aggregates, or all of the five aggregates, are muddled in your own understanding, in regard to your own five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people go through their life using words like matter, feeling, my perception, or my consciousness, my intentions, but the understanding of it, it's completely muddled.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a concoction of various concepts and ideas, never questioned, often self-contradictory.
[SPEAKER_01]: And on top of it then, you try to practice the dhamma, as in keep adding more.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the right practice of dhamma is undoing the ignorance, not adding the right knowledge on top of the ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you undo by reverting back to questioning the basic nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not denying it, not affirming it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just putting it in question, so that you can see what is there, enduring, that you just refer to as feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is there?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, there's no feeling, there's nothing, there's nothing, nothing's permanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another third-person view, assumption in regard to your own experience, that you just jump into out of your views and ideas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Put all that aside, ask yourself, feeling, feeling, what is my feeling right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'm feeling pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that designation, feeling pleasant, what is the feeling aspect of that pleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you refer to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if there was nothing to refer to, you wouldn't use that word as a designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be just a hollow sound, just a pointless sound, and we don't use pointless sounds like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even when there's something not understood, in the case of Puthujjana, the nature is aggregate, it's completely muddled, eh... it still refers to something, and that's the starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that something you are referring to, when you say, my perception?
[SPEAKER_00]: If I just go back to that, your will, again, like if I say it,
[SPEAKER_00]: If I question, is my mind defiled?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I mean by defilement?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to question yourself rightly... See, the Buddha said that the monk will do that, which means he already has undone all these wrong views about what ill will is, what defilement is.
[SPEAKER_01]: He already knows these things, so then that kind of questioning can be right and productive.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, you can start.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is my mind defiled?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so what is then defilement?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I mean by defilement?
[SPEAKER_01]: I know what defilement means in theory, in the dictionary definition, in the Pali Text Society dictionary.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know what defilement is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what is it for me when I say defilement?
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I referring to?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then look at what you're referring to and see if it matches what you think defilement is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you start to undo the layers of this muddled thinking in regard to the basic phenomena of your experience, the nature of phenomena of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of, like, ill-will again, so I'll go back to...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the resistance in regard to something, to a feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you need to know what feeling is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you look what ill-will is... Well, that's how you also know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't think, like, I need to know this before I can do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you realize how much you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: By knowing how much you don't know, you know exactly how much you need to learn.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't start the questioning,
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't even know how much you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the worst type of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I referring to as ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would I describe it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, first and obvious, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ill-will is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a resistance towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can take further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you can go into, like, psychologizing mode.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, that's you assuming the third-person view in regard to your own experience of your world.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you want to do is repeating the question, if your mind won't stay on it, if it hasn't been learned, if it hasn't been taught how to think properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep repeating it and keep dwelling on the topic without giving in to self, kind of, in... fabricated third-person explanations based on the theory you read.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nor do you mystify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, ill-will is inexplicable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you just explain it by calling it inexplicable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is clearly its property, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it's not truly inexplicable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means your own designation contradicted itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those are the criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't contradict yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't assume the third-person view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how else would you then describe the ill-will?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just not wanting... Well, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: See?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not wanting.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we said, what's the basic characteristic of ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which one is it that you don't want?
[SPEAKER_01]: The unpleasantness of ill-will or the ill-will?
[SPEAKER_00]: The unpleasantness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize if, say, theoretically, ill-will would not be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how when people say they have anger problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have anger problem when they start basically, like, bitterly indulging.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order for them to undo that ill-will, they first need to stop enjoying it and see it for what it is, which is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's because it's unpleasant that you... Well, you have to deal with it because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already get rid of it, you're fine enjoying it, you get rid of it by dismissing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, engaging in ill-will is a form of pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a form of trying to escape the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first and foremost then, if you want to overcome ill-will, you have to stop acting habitually.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the habit in this case, as we just clarified, is trying to avoid unpleasant feeling, displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are able to hold the unpleasant feeling for as long as it endures, you won't give in to ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you have no anger problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anger problem is when you can't restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, all of this now, that we just described, came from basic questioning.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is ill-will, in my experience?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not what is ill-will for me, as in it can mean something else for somebody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the universal characteristics of the phenomenon of ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, there is resistance in regard to that displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, you then give in to the proposed actions of your real will.
[SPEAKER_01]: They not just distract you from displeasure, but offer certain, like, amount of pleasurable just... justified pleasure through, like, oh, well, justice has been served, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: He done me... he done me harm.
[SPEAKER_01]: I...
[SPEAKER_01]: I retaliated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I feel good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or things like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or just... just generally letting it out there, affecting others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, abandon ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: He abandons ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what motivates ill-will, then, is running away from your own displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to unmotivate the act of ill-will, stop running away from your own displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no outlet for your will, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cut at its root.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for, like, envy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's mentioned here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Envy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, same.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is envy in its fundamental characteristic?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it pleasant or unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you take that feeling for granted, you will take your attitude towards that feeling for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling of this pleasure is taken for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Me not wanting this pleasure is taken for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the
[SPEAKER_01]: The output of that attitude is going to be envy, ill-will, sensuality, for that matter, any of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Evil wishes, deceitfulness, everything unwholesome will come simply because you are unaware and muddled in regard to the nature of the present enduring feeling in your own experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not yesterday, not tomorrow, not before or after.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right here, right now, while you are being engaging or restraining from engaging in all those acts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you... if you uproot the aptitude in regard to the presently arisen feeling in your experience, you uproot the whole kind of laid out, paved out ways of the proliferation of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you go around trying to chase every individual unwholesome and trim it back, yeah, good luck with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the Buddha said,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a palm stump killed at its root.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't go around trimming the branches that have been proliferated this way or that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize, well, that's a waste of effort and certainly not going to solve the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: You kill its roots and then whatever's been proliferated, you don't care about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No amount of pathways of ill-will will make a difference when there is no ill-will to go along those pathways.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's just like a palm stump dried up, cut up,
[SPEAKER_01]: Destroyed at its root.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't grow again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, there was a passage that probably many, many people in the past and in the future would just read over and, of course, you abandon unwholesome, you get joy and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole teaching is in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't know what unwholesome is, you won't know what wholesome is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you then do that question that the Buddha talks about?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'll tell you how people might think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I don't care.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, for example, it's in this, it's in this that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, well, if the sūtra says it, then it's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, this...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what I've just read there, the abandoning of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: He does this.
[SPEAKER_00]: He abandons wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he gets right view and he's happy because he's purified of evil and wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, his mind becomes composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, samādhi is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as a result of that composure and that abandonment of evil and wholesome states, it goes into hereby it's pervading one quarter with the mind imbued with kindness.
[SPEAKER_00]: With a mind, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll say what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without hostility and without ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: But,
[SPEAKER_00]: Somehow, this whole sutta has been turned upside down in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, one assumes, I will abide pervading one quarter with the mind with loving-kindness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, I will eventually abandon ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will eventually gain samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will eventually be purified of all evil and wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you read the sutta,
[SPEAKER_01]: You already need to understand first, fully, what wholesome and unwholesome is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to abandon the wrong view fully.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to become sotāpanna, then be glad, because you're free from unwholesome, and then you pervade your experience with that gladness, which is brahma-vihāras.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all to make you just recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a result of right understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a method or some visualization or whatever, wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will then miraculously cure you from your ill-will and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very easy to assume that, okay, now, if I just... Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: The opposite of ill-will is... No, because people...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, because people are used to doing things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the ignorant mind does.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, I'm doing this, I'm doing that, I'm choosing this, I'm choosing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you start telling them, okay, but now you need to understand the nature of your action.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they would say, okay, so what do I do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is the threshold.
[SPEAKER_01]: What can be done?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I must do something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they might see the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might get the hints and see the signs of, ah, understanding the nature of action frees you from action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's insightful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're still gonna have trouble finding a direction to go, to see that, without doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when you come in clear instruction, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand unwholesome, you understand wholesome, you abandon the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, but what do I do in order to do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, tell me how to move.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see, it's only natural then, to pervert the order and assume.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so I will sit in my room, and I will send positive thoughts to my enemies, and I will think well about everyone, and I will be kind, and I will do this, and I will do this, and I will do this, and through that magical doing, I'm gonna have a magical result of being free from action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through doing action, I'm gonna free myself from doing action.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they remain oblivious to that blatant contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not about what you do, it's whether you understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: The phenomenon of doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this case, ill-will, ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know what you should not do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't engage with ill-will at its face value, as in be restrained and develop virtue beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can do that type of negative action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abstain from unwholesome action.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do I do next then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, next, ask yourself the questions whether you even understand
[SPEAKER_01]: Things in your experience, presently there, because when you say, oh, my ill-will is sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm currently restraining my acts of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say somebody says that, and if you were to ask them, okay, so what is that ill-will that you designate to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: If they give any answer except the answer that pertains to the present situation, it's going to be the wrong answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that ill-will is there when they made that designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if they have to resort to theory or explanation, it means they don't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just serve another view that stands in place of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another assumption of what ill-will is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, as long as you serve assumptions, you serve upādāna, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You serve your own holding through taking things at face value.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody says, oh, currently I'm experiencing my mind is in a state of ill-will on account of such and such reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Put reasons aside, allow the presently arisen ill-will to endure, and then investigate that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not through theory, not through third-person view, not through psychologizing, but what are the characteristics of this experience as a whole affected by ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just what we've done ten minutes ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the first and obvious
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so the characteristic of ill-will is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could I regard that to be a universal characteristic of ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, is there sometimes ill-will that I don't feel pressured or sort of affected by?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, there isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could safely say, you're not ultimately sure, but you don't need to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because at least you're thinking on the basic of presently enduring things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not on the basis of theory, scholastic investigation, mystical, whatever, psychologizing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presently, what you're experiencing, that's what you're trying to clarify to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just through what it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Looking at the signs and tokens of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so, ill will...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, my acts on account of ill-will, things I used to do, things that I'm restraining now, and things that I hope I won't do in the future,
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, an obvious thing that very few people would actually see on the basis of presently enduring things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, many people keep the precepts perfectly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And still remain putuginous, completely no understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, because they haven't understood it, any of it, on the presently enduring basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start dealing with it, you realize, within two sentences, that's why you must... it's not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You must restrain first, because it doesn't come from the arisen experience of ill-will, or centrality for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's my doing on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if I keep doing that at its face value, how can I free myself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, basically, if I pressure you and you cannot help by responding, I will always know my pressure works.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to free yourself from my pressure over you, yet you can't help responding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you say, well, I want to be free, the fact that you keep responding to my pressure, I know you're not free.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first, you have to stop responding to the pressure of your will or the pressure of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, virtue is non-negotiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtue comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you... then there's already a basis of clarity there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why I must... and when there's clarity in regard to restraint, means there is understanding in regard to the nature of restraint, which means you're doing it less blindly now and you're actually seeing how it pertains to the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not direct and you also understand that.
[SPEAKER_01]: My restraint does not miraculously result in freedom from ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you know exactly why is it necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, so I have to stop giving in to the pressure in order to free myself from the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you, again, you don't see it as a theory, you see it on a presently enduring basis of that ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can carry on with that questioning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so now that I am restrained, that I have clarified that with relative certainty that universal characteristic of ill-will, it's unpleasant in pressuring me,
[SPEAKER_01]: Go a step further and then, as we've done, so what is it then that's unpleasant in it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a particular content or just... Do you have a say over which aspect is going to bother you, of that ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you ever say which part will be unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just has a reason, has a package, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ill-will, unpleasant pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of this or this, or this or that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, ill-will in its nature pressures you, so it's being felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the experience of ill-will means experience of feeling displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, really now, you're not concerned with ill-will anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're concerned with the gratuitous attitude of craving for the absence of the disagreeable feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you carry on the same questioning, as we've done in other talks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so, feeling, feeling, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the feeling when I refer to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, not before, after, yesterday, tomorrow, a new theory, new suit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right here, right now, on the basis of ill will, that I've been self-investigating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me ask myself a further question now, that I've discerned there is a feeling behind it, that's where the problem is rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the presently enduring
[SPEAKER_01]: Disagreeable feeling of a particularly manifested ill will.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that unpleasant feeling, what is its nature?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you describe it in most general terms?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, the Buddha... No, it doesn't matter what the Buddha said or who said what.
[SPEAKER_01]: For you, right now, that feeling of disagreeable that keeps enduring for while we're talking all of this, how would you describe it in your own terms?
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't worry about being right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as pretty much everybody I would ever ask this question, said, oh, well, it's just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be the common thread.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, it's just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: If something is just there, you have no idea why or how for whether it's just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if something that's just there, that you're just subjected to it, that you can only sort of act secondarily, so to speak, in response to, but you can't prevent from arising,
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are you regarding that thing as yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you taking your attitude of response at face value?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your attitude of response implies that you can do something about that thing just being there oppressing you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you look at it closely, you realize, I have even no idea how this thing came to be, how long it will be, let alone how to, like, make it go away when I want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha would say, oh, well, if the pleasantness feeling is yours, how about that unpleasant feeling or neutral feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, feeling is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, well, which one?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if feeling were truly yours, you would have only one feeling that you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would never experience feelings that you don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because more often than not, you experience feelings that you don't want, you realize that when you want feelings, you actually realize, oh, actually, even that is not in my control.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the nature of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all rooted in the same response towards a reasoned feeling, craving, response of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And response, where I use the word response, it's not a process, it's not a response in time, it's a simultaneously present attitude to the simultaneously present phenomenon of that particular feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, it shouldn't be there, but for Putujana, it is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is his starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether it's ill-will, whether it's any envy, what is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: You bring it down and it's going to come down to how it's being felt, that experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's going to come down to whether you're trying to indulge the unwholesome, get rid of it, or distract yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Greed, lust, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you remove lust, aversion, delusion, you've removed the entire universe of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Possibilities of unwholesome cannot manifest then.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so, one sees it, oh, I can't, I can't see any craving, yeah, in regard to fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because you don't see the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, so, if you say, I can't see any craving, the answer, basically, can be only two answers.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're either an arahant,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no third option.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is in common to resisting the feeling, welcoming the feeling, covering up the feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's in common to these three things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Except feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, craving, for many people, they think they understood craving, they understood the word craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how would you then describe that craving that's in common to these three attitudes towards the feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: What would be the characteristics of the craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: An attitude of... an attitude of pressure, some kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, like, that's normal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people will stop and think that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go back to the present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: How am I feeling right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm feeling neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the Buddha said, in regard to neutral feeling, there is a tendency towards ignorance, towards distraction, towards oblivion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the tendency is where the craving is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would be then, in your own words,
[SPEAKER_01]: The characteristic of that tendency of the kind of present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're not necessarily doing the distraction, you can recognize the tendency to do so, in regard to neither unpleasant or pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: I feel wanting, just wanting to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanting, but wanting is already the result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, so, when you want something different from what it is now, enduring, how would you describe that?
[SPEAKER_00]: We're resisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who resists?
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: Me, resisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're resisting the reason-feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you want to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: I want it to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to replace it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you go back to see what you're resisting, as we've just done here, you realize it has a reason on its own, enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you want to override it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize how futile that is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the only way you can override something is if you have a say.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if something is just there on its own, oppressing you, or isn't on its own, enduring on its own, you are subjected to it, it's not subjected to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you entertaining notions of overriding it, when you can't even conceive where or how that would be possible?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you realize you can entertain notions of overriding it by not understanding what it is that you resist and try to override.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, ignorance results in that craving, or rather, ignorance fuels the craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you stop ignoring the nature of that which is there that you're trying to resist, can you then still engage in the acts of craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, and it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think there would be a... you wouldn't have to try to un-engage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you don't ignore it, there is no room for craving or non-craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, well, it's absence of craving, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no room for wanting or not wanting, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because both can be a craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want this, I don't want this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you crave.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as we just clarified, again, on the basis of the present enduring feeling, if you stop ignoring the obvious universal nature of that enduring phenomenon that you're feeling,
[SPEAKER_01]: You will then stop entertaining the notions of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, no matter what you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter what you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you've understood the nature of feeling in general.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you stopped ignoring the right nature of feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's when people are mindfulness and then like touching, moving, moving, looking, looking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not mindfulness of everything and nothing at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's mindfulness of feelings, thoughts or intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, they're going to boil down to feeling and craving towards feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mindfulness of the present enduring feeling in the background of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the present mood?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the basis of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it pleasant, unpleasant, neutral?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you don't lose the sight of.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't lose the sight of it, you cannot ignore its nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the nature of these things that have a reason for you, the Buddha said himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's anicca and dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then, your experience will be anatta, if you see that nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, if you see the nature...
[SPEAKER_01]: But, basically, like, all of these attitudes of resisting, craving, they all come from the view of, I am in charge, I am in control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, I will replace this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, I will make this stay longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you could see, like, even that I am in control and I will do all of this,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because of your ignorance of what you're trying to replace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignorance of the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, if you press yourself far enough in the questioning, the answer is going to be, oh, well, it's just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how, why, how long, for what reason, the feeling is just there and it's felt like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It oppresses me, I don't oppress it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you cannot even conceive, even people who are full-on, out of other, believe in their self, self-centered, whatever, megalomaniac, even they could not ignore that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that all of your sense of self and your responses are secondary to the fact the thing has arisen first on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you are subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what Nietzsche
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, recognizing the characteristics of these things that determine you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said, um, sabe saṅkāra anicca, sabe saṅkāra dukkha, sabe dhamma anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the self-view, sense of self, is on the level of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not on the level... well, it's related to the level of saṅkāra, but it's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like everything is impermanent, everything is suffering, everything is not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's a third-person view about everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you want to see that presently arisen things for me, that determine me, are arisen on its own, and they're oppressing me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those things I've been talking about, that's exactly what anicca and dukkha is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, like, pleasure is oppressing you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha is not like pain and pain everywhere, just pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha is being oppressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the questioning we've been doing, again, the entire dhamma is contained in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anicca, dukkha, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could see, if you discern
[SPEAKER_01]: The peripheral feeling, the mood that you are in, whatever you're doing particularly, this or that, we're not talking, the background of your mood, what is... what is the fundamental?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you label it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Positive, negative, or maybe neutral?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's a bit positive.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel light and easy, whatever else, means it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is universal nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that pleasure and use can endure for days sometimes, even in Putujana's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or something bothersome.
[SPEAKER_01]: This disagreeable feeling can fundamentally endure for days.
[SPEAKER_01]: On a particular level, you can have this pleasant feeling and this pleasant, but they're particular when you're looking at the most general nature of what's overall being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the craving is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you stop ignoring what's overall being felt, and in order to stop ignoring that, you have to stop giving in to the particular pursuits
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you will be aware of your mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be aware of the enduring feeling on that fundamental basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you are aware of the right... the more you're aware of the feeling on that right level, the less you will be able to entertain things that directly
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basic composure of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to do a proper vipassana, then, on the basis of that composure, you ask these questions we've just done.
[SPEAKER_01]: What would be the universal characteristic?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would I describe this enduring feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: It clearly now endures for two or three days.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not saying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just happens to be pleasant, so I don't feel threatened by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But,
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't feel threatened by the particular pleasure of that feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to look beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's universal?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is... You can ask yourself, what is in common to this fundamentally pleasant mood that I have?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's in common to this and to unpleasant mood that I had or will have in the future?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the neutral mood?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop being concerned with pleasant, unpleasant, neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start looking at the nature of that feeling, that is pleasant, unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, again, you don't need to, oh, it's anicca, it's anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you say that, then ask yourself, what is anicca for me?
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I designating by anicca?
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to discern the characteristics of that feeling, and those characteristics will be anicca and dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the Buddha himself said, he didn't invent the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't... he created this.
[SPEAKER_01]: He rediscovered it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why freedom from ignorance is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, if you look at these things genuinely, correctly, sufficiently, that is their nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, I'm not its creator.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, it's just there now, but when it isn't, it won't be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, it's permanent, impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, it cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, it's just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I bring it into me?
[SPEAKER_01]: and assimilate its whole domain, make it mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can get closer to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have this attitude or that attitude, more attitude, less attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the duration of any of that, that thing will always be there on its own, enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the... what is the... what is... what is another characteristic of that... what is the universal characteristic of
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasant feeling, unpleasant feeling, or neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in theory, but on the basis of pleasant feeling that you're currently feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasant mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: We said that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive where it... how the feeling... You can explain using modern science and whatnot, but all of that is secondary to the fact that this thing is just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't go through it and see what's behind the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your bottom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I have no choice in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no choice in the matter, which means, who is, who is basically subordinate to who?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are your feelings subordinate to you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or actually, your own choice and intention, volition is subordinate to the present-realism feeling that's just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it oppresses you, it controls you, and that's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we already described anicca and dukkha on account of the characteristics that anybody who starts this questioning can start seeing on account of presently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, I insist presently enduring feeling must be on the level of the most general background of the mood that you are in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not on account of, oh, I'm looking this, I'm feeling light in my body and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is secondary to a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But mood never is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can, you can, you can, like, tell yourself you're a master controller of your experience, but moods, fundamentally good, bad or neutral, is something that always comes underneath you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, if you go that far to discern the nature of the feeling, or you have to go that far to discern the nature of the feeling, because that's the way that you cannot re-pervert it back, so to speak, to being mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any lesser feeling than that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Can be appropriated easily because your sense of self remains kind of impartial to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not really the feeling you're looking for.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fundamentally, is it positive, negative or neutral?
[SPEAKER_00]: That you have no say in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will arrive at that through ill-will, questioning the ill-will, questioning anything unwholesome, questioning centrality,
[SPEAKER_01]: All right.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll arrive at the same point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing saṅkharas as anicca, as oppressing your dukkha, and then, automatically, you will not be able to entertain the notion that you are master controller of your whole experience, when you realize you are the sub... you are the one subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, that experience of I'm the master controller is seen, oh, this is not my... this is not the master and controller.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that experience becomes the experience of anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where anicca is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like what your self sees.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's what undermines your sense of self, which is the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why somebody who has discerned this, as we would say, would just stay mindful of manifestation of the aggregates coming and going, arising and passing, or whatever translation is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what the characteristics are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through staying mindful of it, you cannot ignore them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through not ignoring them, you cannot proliferate craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through not proliferating craving, you cannot suffer anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with, like, intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You find there is an intention there, towards...
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with any aggregate, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, the feeling is where things converge, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: You intend here and there because you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if people were not starting with wrong views, then, in theory, they could pick up any aggregate and question it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But everybody starts with wrong views, and the convergence of their wrong views is on craving, and that's where the feeling is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, unless you start undoing it from that basis, and you, say, start thinking about intentions of the nature of viññāṇa and whatnot, you're not going to be thinking on the present of presently enduring phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can, theoretically, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say consciousness-consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say consciousness, in English or in Pali or whatever language, what am I referring to in this experience, right here, right now, while I'm saying that question?
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I referring to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Tell me the characteristics of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that would be much harder, much more subtle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind you, consciousness is the most refined of all, as the Buddha said himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if one does that on the basis of the presently enduring mood and feeling, then it becomes actually fully intelligible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people, most people's relation with Buddhist practice is magical almost.
[SPEAKER_01]: I believe that through being virtuous, I believe that through being good, I believe that through doing this method and technique, I believe through the reading suttas, I'm going to have the experience of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I believe in rebirth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I believe in everything basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: I believe that me doing this to the left is going to result in these things to the right.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no connection between the two that I can see, or that I don't have to fabricate for myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The definition of the one who is free from wrong view is he knows wholesome as wholesome and unwholesome as unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he knows why good is good and bad is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not just believing in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why he's free from Sīla Bhāgavatam's virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's my duty, you know, to sit and watch my nostrils because how else can I become enlightened?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but why is that your duty?
[SPEAKER_01]: Ask yourself that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like through fabricating answers based on, you know, the commentarial text you read and just providing back the information.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presently arisen cause has been presently understood and that's the freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, do you understand presently arisen things and does that understanding presently, simultaneously, free you from them?
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you never start questioning it on that level, how do you expect to find it out?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Buddha said, deal with the knife.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, keep digging.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, keep digging back or in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Undoing the layers of your views and what you think phenomena are and feelings are and intentions are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just, oh, keep fabricating further and you'll arrive at the right goal through your state of putusha.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way to arrive at the goal is to undo, dismantle, stop feeding, stop providing nutrients for your state of putuji.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's usually completely the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, that's always the completely opposite direction from where people usually tend to go in their practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even when somebody approaches the sutta and says, oh, yeah, yeah, this, this, this, this makes sense, makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of building further, you have to look back now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so I think I understood this sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I a sotāpanna as a result of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because truly understanding a sutta will mean at least the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it the sutta's fault?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it translation's fault?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, maybe to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: The translation's fault, not the sutta's fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: But really, it's your preconceived notions of the terms that you're reading in the sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those notions are wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, your usage of the meanings in the sutta is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you start undoing your notions of the wrong terms with the help of the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you get to read them rightly.